[instrumental music]
[indistinct chattering]
What brings us to
this beautiful place, Lisbon?
A missing person.
Jay Banner. He's 26 years old.
He's a local boy.
He works at some sort
of marine salvage place.
He went surfing yesterday,
and he never came home.
Oh, look at the crabs.
You see the little crab?
Oh, look at the little crabby.
Excuse me.
I'm Agent Lisbon with the CBI.
This is Consultant Patrick Jane.
- Are you, uh, Chief Anson?
- That's right.
These are Jay's roommates,
Tark Mitchum, Vicki Lang.
Welcome.
Oh, come on.
We're not welcome.
You resent us being here
on your turf.
Let me rephrase that,
your, uh..
...your sand,
your sandy coastline.
Not at all.
It's just that Jay's an adult.
Barely been gone a day.
This just seems to me to be
a complete waste of time.
Is this where
he was last seen?
Yeah, him and Jeeter.
That's our other roommate.
They went out yesterday
for dawn patrol.
That's an early morning
surf session.
I know.
And Jay didn't come home
all night.
I found his board right here,
which means he didn't drown.
I mean, he wouldn't drown.
He was a fish.
So I thought,
what if he's been kidnapped?
So, I called the cops.
You called your father.
The congressman?
I wanted the big guns, chief.
That board's a custom.
So either Jay was very rich
or very serious
about his surfing.
He's serious, dude.
He's trying to go pro.
All he needs is that
one big endorsement.
Okay. Well, don't mind me.
I'm gonna take a little stroll,
soak up the atmosphere.
'Oh! So gorgeous.'
Did he have any troubles?
Drug problems?
Bad relationships?
No, I mean..
No.
- Shut up, Tark.
- Wh..
Um, me and Jay used to hook up,
not for a long time.
When did you break up?
We weren't dating.
It was casual.
- That's how Jay wanted it.
- 'Oh!'
What is he doing?
Big gun, huh?
Lisbon!
Flies and crabs!
Excuse me?
Crabs are scavengers,
so I followed one.
Led me to this swarm of flies,
and look.
[flies buzzing]
'I found Jay Banner.'
[Lisbon]
The victim worked
for this outfit here.
Santa Marta Salvage.
Excuse me?
Excuse me, ma'am. Hi.
Are you Greta Marshall?
Uh, yeah. Sure am.
I'm Agent Lisbon
with the CBI.
We just wanted to ask you
a few questions
about your employee,
Jay Banner.
Jay.
Oh, that was such
a terrible thing, awful.
News travels fast, huh?
Small town, big ears.
You should talk to my husband
too. Um, we co-own the company.
Hey, Greg! Honey!
What are you doing?
I'm just checking
the nav equipment.
Oh, checking the nav equipment.
We had a big storm
come in here last month.
Stirred everything up.
She hit an uncharted sandbar
and, well..
...knocked the sonar around.
Ouch!
Hey, what's up?
Greg?
Oh, my God.
'What are you doing here?'
You live here?
In California?
Yeah, 14 years now.
Uh, Greta's from Santa Marta.
My-my wife, I, um..
Honey, this is,
uh, Teresa Lisbon.
This is Teresa Lisbon?
TheTeresa Lisbon?
The one and only.
Uh, Greg and I used to date when
we were kids back in Chicago.
Yeah, we were engaged,
in fact.
Okay. Uh, let me guess.
You broke it off?
I was way too young.
Yeah, well, of course.
Did she break your heart?
[chuckles]
I wouldn't say that.
- No.
- Yeah, you did.
'Cause he was still talking
about you when we met.
[laughs]
Heartbreaker.
We just w-wanted to ask you
some questions about Jay.
Is there somewhere
more private we can talk?
Sure, yeah,
we got offices up there.
Do you have any tea?
'Cause this could take a while.
Mm-hmm.
[theme music]
[Lisbon]
'How long did Jay work here?'
Well, about a year.
Until last week.
He-he quit.
[Lisbon]
'Oh!'
[Greg]
'Yeah, lately he had
something on his mind.'
I mean, he was only doing this
for side money, anyways
while he did his surf thing.
Mom.
[Greg]
Hey, baby.
I need money for the movie.
Excuse me?
May I please have money
for the movie?
- And popcorn.
- Here.
Hi. I'm Patrick Jane.
That's, uh, the Teresa Lisbon.
Hi. I'm Lauren Tayback.
Hi, Lauren.
Okay, go.
Have fun, babe. Bye.
- Okay.
- Bye.
Nice to meet you,
Lauren Tayback.
Wow. How many do you have?
Uh, we got Lauren,
Maddy, and Sally.
[whistles]
Wow.
Breeder.
Yeah.
Uh, you didn't, uh,
like Jay much, did you?
What? No, he was
a great diver, man.
Yes, but you didn't
like him. Why?
It's...I have three daughters,
alright?
And I wouldn't want any of them
being treated the way
Jay treated women.
How is that?
Use 'em and toss 'em.
Uh, why did Jay quit?
[chuckles]
Oh, why do people quit?
Hmm.
You know,
they just quit.
- Excuse me.
- See you, babe.
She's nice.
[Van Pelt]
Uh, Rigsby's
taking a personal day.
The baby's sick,
and Sarah has court.
He's really embracing
the daddy thing.
Yeah.
[knocking on door]
You guys the cops?
Yeah.
CBI. Are you Jay Banner's
other roommate?
No. Uh, I'm the landlord.
Lance Gladstone.
I, uh, own this place.
I live in the, uh, back house.
I was just gonna do
some work on these steps.
Keep my mind off Jay,
you know?
You have keys to let us in?
Sure.
[keys jangling]
What?
[Van Pelt]
'Jeeter, how long
were you and Jay roommates?'
Three years. Jay and me.
We were both trying
to qualify for the pro tour.
And Jay was really close
to inking a deal
with Oakley, you know?
Mind if I open a window?
Please. This smoke
plays hell with my asthma.
I have a prescription.
I have anxiety.
Especially now.
Jay was my best friend.
And you two went surfing
together yesterday morning?
For a while, and then
it got kind of blown out.
So I went to work.
I left at 7:00.
Jay was alive
when you left?
Yes. God, yes.
He was standing there
on the beach.
Coroner's preliminary report
says Jay died yesterday morning
around the time
you were with him.
Did you see anything unusual?
Maybe someone else on the beach?
No. No one on the beach.
But there was a boat coming in.
Coming in?
That's weird for that hour.
Most boats are going out.
- You see the name of the boat?
- No.
Couldn't see
with the marine layer.
Running lights weren't on.
Interesting.
Somebody didn't want to be seen.
Marine salvage.
What is that, exactly?
We do lots of different stuff,
like water rescue
harbor clean-up,
wreck diving ops.
Wreck diving ops? That sounds
like treasure hunting.
[chuckles]
No, not so much.
We got a lot of old ships
on the ocean floor around here.
'That's pictures of some of them
on the wall there.'
But they've all been
picked over for decades now.
There's nothing down there
but some..
...cool wrecks
to dive around.
Uh, the Brother Jonathan
uh, the Golden State,
and the Fremont..
Those wreck diving ops,
can you do those alone?
No, not if you wanna
live long.
One guy handles the winch,
the other one dives, always.
- Hmm.
- Why?
Lisbon, we should get going.
Uh, Greg.
Real pleasure to meet you.
Thank you very much
for the tea. Take care.
Greg..
...thank you for your time.
Jeeter's really torn up.
So he and Jay got along?
No...jealousy,
arguments over girls?
Best buds.
Jeeter's a good guy.
I'm gonna prorate the rent
till they find another roommate.
- Was Jay the big earner?
- No way.
'I mean, all these guys
are living hand to mouth.'
Jay could hardly buy food.
He was talking about moving out
and living on his boat.
What boat?
Some cheap, old powerboat.
'Jay had a berth somewhere.'
[dramatic music]
Oh, here you go, man.
Thanks.
[music continues]
Coke.
Looks like enough
to sell.
Aw, dude,
that's seriously uncool.
It's a lightning bolt. I've seen
this before in Sacramento.
Jay was in the city last week.
Said he had business.
No sign of a murder weapon
on the beach.
Coroner thinks
it was something heavy.
Possibly metal.
Hey, chief. Any sign
of the victim's powerboat?
Not yet.
It's not at the docks.
Jay lost his berth
for non-payment of rent.
Might have it trailered
somewhere on land.
We're happy to give you
some extra people to search.
If that boat is in Santa Marta,
I'll find it.
No help from CBI is necessary,
but you know what?
Thank you very much.
[female #1]
'Hello?'
Isn't there a coke dealer
in Sacramento..
...uses a lightning bolt
as a logo?
[female #1]
'Well, hello to you, too.'
'Lightning bolt..'
Tookie Burroughs used
to use a lightning bolt.
Maybe he still does.
The victim
had dealer-quantity coke
with that logo on every bag.
Oh, well, you know,
I know Tookie from way back.
- If you want, I could--
- 'No, no.'
Don't even think about it.
I just need a name.
And I'll take it from there.
You're no fun at all.
Our victim was a semi-pro
surfer, name of Jay Banner.
You can ask around about him.
See if he was
a real player or not.
Jay Banner. Okay.
I love you, boo.
Come home soon.
[Cho]
Bye, babe.
Was that Summer?
Yeah.
Sorry to be direct, but what's
going on with you and her?
[sighs]
She's my confidential informant.
Right..
...but we're not allowed
to date CIs.
You're givingme
dating advice?
As a friend,
even if she weren't your CI..
...are you sure
she's someone you should..
...be around?
Let's go.
[engine starts]
[Jane]
'Well, Greg seems very nice.'
I am not discussing it
with you.
Nice, solid, dependable.
I can see why you dumped him.
- I mean it, Jane.
- Alright.
- Seriously.
I didn't dump him.
We both decided to take a break.
Mm-hmm.
The old, let's take a break.
[Lisbon]
I did not dump him.
[Tookie]
'Sixty bucks.'
Sixty? Come on, Tookie.
What do you say 40
for old time's sake?
Sure, after you do me
for old time's sake.
[chuckles]
Is this the same stuff you sell
to my boy, Jay from Santa Marta?
'Cause that-that was good.
- Jay?
- Mmm.
Jay Banner.
[cell phone ringing]
- Oh, yeah. The surf punk.
- Mm-hmm.
I like that dude.
He's hardcore.
Hang on a second.
- Ahem.
- Yeah? So speak.
Oh!
'Yeah, y-you tell him
I told him to shove it down'
'his mother's throat,
the little punk bitch.'
Moron.
So I heard Jay was, uh,
in some beef with some people.
- Oh, yeah? I never heard that.
- No?
It's good stuff.
See you around, Tookie.
Yeah, see you, babes.
Summer, you here?
[water running]
I got Indian.
[Summer]
'Hi, baby, um..'
Hey, I'm gonna hang
with my girlfriends tonight.
'Do you mind? Rain check?'
You come out
and talk to me, okay?
[chuckles]
'Babe, I'm in the shower.'
Something's wrong.
Come on out.
I mean it. Right now.
'Kimball, this is my house,
not yours.'
'I'll come out
when I feel like it.'
- Step away from the door.
- 'No.'
'Kimball, don't.'
Ah!
You never listen.
It was just a mugging.
It's no big deal.
Where?
Downtown.
Some punk kid.
It's just bruises. I'm fine.
- Ow!
- Sorry.
[sighing]
If it was just a mugging..
...why would you not
want me to see you?
Hmm?
Summer, look at me.
Tell me the truth.
Did you go see that dealer?
No.
You went to see
Tookie Burroughs.
You asked him
about Jay Banner.
No, I swear I didn't.
Okay, fine.
It wasn't a mugging.
But..
I ran into some guy
I used to party with and..
...he got mad when I told him I
didn't want to do that anymore.
Happens all the time,
alright?
Can we please
just forget about it?
What was his name?
This guy you used to know.
I don't know his name?
I-I don't, I don't know what..
I remember Bob or..
...Steve.
I don't know, Kimball.
Please.
Can we just forget
about it, please?
Get some rest.
- Morning, boss.
- Morning. How's Ben?
Oh, yeah, he's better, thanks.
It's some kind of ear infection.
Easy to knock out
with antibiotics.
Gave him a fever and made him,
you know, throw up.
- A lot of throw up.
- Aw, poor thing.
Did we have any luck
finding The Hang Ten?
The victim's powerboat?
Oh! No.
Chief Anson asked all over
Santa Marta. Nothing yet.
Uh, what about the mystery
vessel the roommate saw
coming in? We need to talk
to whoever was on that boat.
Yeah, we talked to every
boater in town. Sorry.
Uh, Rigs, you got something
on your..
- Is that spit-up?
- Mmm. Yeah.
It's from this morning.
I was feeding him,
and he was looking up at me
with those big,
adorable eyes.
And then he barfed.
- Kids, huh?
- Yeah.
You know what?
He's the best thing
that ever happened to me.
Wow. That's great.
Morning, chief.
Trapping those tourists early?
Permit-only spot.
Clearly posted.
They can get it out of impound
if they have $200.
'That's the law.'
There's no tyranny
like petty tyranny.
- Excuse me?
- You heard me.
Where you going?
Research library.
That's the bar.
[blows raspberry]
I'm going to meet Jane
in Santa Marta.
Has Cho been in yet?
- I haven't seen him.
- Alright.
Oh, hey, I interviewed
some of Jay's surfing buddies
and we've got a lead, maybe.
- Yeah?
- Possible angry girlfriend.
Day before the murder,
these guys on the beach
saw Jay getting yelled at
on his cell phone by some woman.
Apparently,
it was pretty heated.
Why didn't the roommates
tell us about her?
Maybe they didn't know.
Oh, and bad news
about our drug dealer.
The guy Banner
was getting the coke from?
'Cho got the name.'
Carlton Tookie Burroughs,
but he's got an alibi.
Sac PD arrested him
the night before the murder
and didn't kick him
until noon the next day.
Hours after Banner died.
Alright, strike Burroughs
from the list.
And if anything with
the girlfriend pops, call me.
Alright.
Hey.
Wayne, you've got
something on your..
Oh, yeah. It's just vomit.
Okay.
Uh, Vicki, another round
for my friends here.
You got it, Mr. Jane.
- Jane--
- Shh.
We're getting
at the best part here.
Fierce storm,
low visibility.
A rock has just torn a hole
in the Fremont's hull
as big as a man.
Carry on, Arkin.
Captain's ordered everyone
to abandon ship.
Mm-hmm.
But it was too late.
'The Fremont sank.'
All 200 souls aboard her.
My grandfather said that
even with all the noise
from the storm that night
you could hear 'em
screaming for help.
Hmm.
Some nights,
people say that
you can still hear
their cries on the wind.
And no one
ever found the gold?
What gold?
The Fremont was
a treasure ship
most famous
in Santa Marta history.
Yeah, went down in 1906.
She was carrying
all the annual treaty payments
for the Indian tribes
up north.
Hmm, crates of gold coins
and bullion
sixty million dollars worth,
today's value.
And it was never found?
Nah, the San Francisco
earthquake happened
a few weeks after the wreck.
They think it buried
the ship for good.
Mm, but you kept looking,
didn't you?
[chuckles]
Yeah, I kept looking.
Eh?
Ten dollar, Liberty Head.
- Gold Eagle.
- Oh!
I found that
the summer of '72.
[both chuckling]
Best damn day of my life.
Hell, I thought
I'd found the Fremont.
I dove every day
for the next seven summers.
I never found
another damn thing.
She's down there.
She's there.
That's a great story,
Arkin.
Thank you.
Neo? Two-dog?
I've gotta go.
I'll see you around.
Thanks for the drink.
Do you think Jay found
the Fremont's treasure?
Well, Jayandhis partner.
You don't treasure hunt alone.
He did know the salvage business
from working for Greg.
- And he had a boat.
- Oh, boat, yes.
I'd like to take
a look at that.
It's missing.
Chief Anson's looking for it.
[Jane]
'Uh, speaking of Chief Anson..'
Hey!
Hey, that's my car.
- What?
- My car.
This is? Yours?
Oh. Is it, really?
Agent, I'm so sorry.
Bill, unhook her.
She's law enforcement.
Hey, chief. Any luck with,
uh, Jay's missing boat?
- It's not in Santa Marta.
- How do you know that?
Because my men and I
searched everywhere in town
every square inch
of landandwater.
- Really?
- Mm-hmm.
Most impressive.
Thank you.
Bill!
Belay that order.
We're gonna ride with you.
I love a tow truck.
- We are? Why?
- Lao-Tzu.
Lao-Tzu?
Famous Chinese philosopher.
What has he got
to do with anything?
Ah, your unconscious
sexual bias
at work there, Lisbon.
You assumed he was a he.
- Well, was he?
- He was.
- Not the point. Get in.
- Oh, my God.
Thank you.
Chief.
[engine starts]
Whoo.
[indistinct chattering]
[Cho]
'Hey.'
[intense music]
[engine starts]
[engine revving]
Yo, yo, get off me, man!
What are you, nuts?
[both grunt]
Carlton Tookie Burroughs.
Police.
[crashes]
[grunting]
[panting]
What the hell's up, yo?
Summer Edgecombe.
Tell me what happened.
Oh, hey, man,
that bitch is yours?
[thwacks]
[thud]
Why'd you hurt her, Tookie?
Dude, I swear to God
if I knew that she had
a cop pimping for her
I would have let her
have it free, alright?
What are you talking about?
She stole my product,
man, like, six grams.
She won't give it back.
Like I'm an idiot?
Come on, man.
I'm not gonna let that slide.
I got a reputation, alright?
[thwacks]
Stay away from her.
[Jane]
Well, thank you.
[sighs]
Lao-Tzu said that if
you search everywhere
yet cannot find
what you are seeking
it is because what you seek
is already in your possession.
Deep.
What kind of boat
did Jay Banner own?
A gray lapstreak.
Hmm, well, Jay
was a smart man
who needed to park his
boat somewhere for free
so why not put someone
else's plates on the trailer
andletit get towed
by the very eager police?
'Where better
to stash your boat'
'than the one place you know'
the policearen'tgonna look?
And then Jay could
slip in through that gate
'anytime he pleased.'
Ah! There it is.
The Hang Ten.
Bingo, and I'm willing to bet
that there is evidence
of Jay's treasure hunt
maybe even the treasure
itself, on board.
[clangs]
Or the killer.
[intense music]
Police! Come out with
your hands in the air!
- Don't shoot.
- 'Greg?'
Sound advice.
You know what
Jane's theory is?
If Jay really did salvage
the Fremont's treasure
he had to have had a partner.
He couldn't have done it alone.
A partner who killed him.
What were you doing
on Jay's powerboat?
He borrowed a life jacket.
I wanted it back.
How did you even know
where to find the boat?
Jay told me.
Greg, stop it. Alright?
Since I'm 17 years old
I can tell when you're lying.
That's funny,
'cause I could never
tell when you
were lying to me.
[door opens]
- Oh. Hey, boss.
- I got this. Thanks.
- 'I thought I was question--'
- Get outta here.
Okay.
See, I know you're lying
because we found
the cleaning equipment.
You were there
to wipe the place down
a good way
to cover your tracks.
Look, I didn't kill him.
The morning of his
death, Jay's roommate
saw a boat
heading toward shore.
That was you. It was your boat.
Look, sometimes
stuff looks bad
and there's
an innocent explanation.
- Okay, what's the explanation?
- You won't believe me.
Try me.
You know..
...it took a long time for
me to get over you, Teresa.
A long time...
but I finally did.
It was your
boat that morning.
Tell me the truth.
Yes, it was my boat. Alright?
I was out fishing.
No luck.
I didn't catch anything.
Talk to me. I can help you.
No, thanks. I'm good.
[bell rings]
- Arkin.
- Mm.
I'd like to ask you a few more
questions about the Fremont.
Then I've got some answers.
"The Fremont?"
Is this about Jay's murder?
Uh, yeah. In fact, there's about
to be a major break in the case.
In that case,
it's on the house.
Oh, thank you.
Oop, it's my phone.
I'm gonna have to take this.
I'll be right back.
[Rigsby]
'Inventory from
the victim's boat.'
- Thanks. We get any prints?
- No.
Tayback must've wiped 'em all.
Hang on.
"Hydraulic pump,
underwater cutting tools."
Those are all salvage
equipment, right?
Yeah, there was a bunch of 'em.
'Expensive stuff.'
Thanks.
No problem.
[indistinct chattering]
Is any of your
equipment missing?
Go away. Greg said
not to speak with you.
Your salvage equipment,
we found some on Jay's boat.
- So?
- So is any of it yours?
If Greg was Jay's partner
in the salvage of the Fremont
they would have used
your company's equipment.
- Greg didn't do this.
- So prove it.
Is any of your gear missing?
No, it's all accounted for.
So Jay used his own gear
which means Greg
wasn't the partner.
Oh, the killer, you mean?
No, of course not.
Greg couldn't hurt anyone.
He incriminated himself.
Greg told me that he was
on a boat going to see Jay
the morning of his death.
I think he was lying
to protect someone else.
[instrumental music]
Yeah.
You.
It was you on that boat.
Greg made me
promise not to tell.
For our girls, he said.
You were having
an affair with Jay.
[sighs]
I love Greg.
But we hit
a rough patch and..
Now with three kids
and the business and..
Well, Jay was just fun and..
No responsibilities.
It was just fun and..
I wanted to imagine
a different life..
...just for a while.
I mean, haven't you
ever wanted to do that?
Tell me what
happened that morning.
I knew I had to
break it off with Jay.
So I took the boat out
in the morning to end it.
And then I came back and I
confessed everything to Greg.
And I begged
for his forgiveness
and he gave it to me.
God bless him.
Did you kill Jay Banner?
No!
No, he was alive
when I left.
But when Greg and I found
out that he'd been killed
he said we had
to keep it a secret.
He wanted to protect me.
That gives Greg strong
motive to kill him.
Well, he couldn't have..
...because he was
at home with the girls.
And besides, you know him.
You really think
he could kill someone?
[cell phone ringing]
Excuse me.
Jane, what's up?
[Jane on phone]
'Lisbon, get over'
'to Jay Banner's house'
'as fast as possible.'
There's excitement afoot.
'Good.'
'Well, she's on her way.'
What the hell's
going on here?
Yeah, I mean, no offense,
but...what he said.
Well, chief, we need to execute
a thorough and exhaustive
search of these premises.
And what are we looking for?
Treasure.
[birds squawking]
♪ Cases of Bacardi chasers ♪
♪ Chasing me all over town ♪
♪ 'Cause he knows I'm wasted ♪
♪ Facing time again
on Rikers Island ♪
♪ And I won't get out ♪
[Cho]
'Hey.'
Hey!
What?
Hi.
Where is it?
Where's what?
The cocaine you
stole from Burroughs.
He said that?
[gasps]
He's a liar.
I didn't steal any cocaine.
I swear to God, Cho.
I would never steal co--
Summer, don't do this.
Uh.
[chuckles]
[whispers]
Okay, fine.
[sighs]
I lied.
But you got to admit,
I kinda fooled you.
I had you
a little bit fooled.
Give it to me.
No. It's no big deal.
Tookie just thinks
he's dangerous.
I've been beaten far
worse for a lot less.
[shouting]
Give it to me!
Fine. Be that way.
Look, I'm sorry.
You know, I-I-I..
I know I've been bad.
It's just..
I've been so bored.
And this was such a rush.
Summer, I had
to stop myself
from hurting
him badly.
I could have killed him.
You understand me?
God...that's kind of hot.
What's the hell
is wrong with you?
You're really messed up,
you know that?
Well, duh!
Like you're not?
No! What are you doing?
Stop it! Are you nuts?
It was mine!
I worked for it, Cho!
I'm a cop! How did you
think this was gonna go?
[crying]
[clatters]
[instrumental music]
[indistinct chattering on radio]
Kitchen and den are clear.
Copy that.
- So is the attic.
- Roger.
- Jane, what's going on?
- Treasure hunt.
- Here?
- Gold's heavy.
And it's hard to transport.
Difficult to store.
They had to hide
the treasure someplace.
Probably near wherever they
brought it into shore.
To keep it safe before
they could sell the gold
but why look here?
Uh, Jeeter?
You were Jay's best friend.
Jay was tricky, sly, always
a couple of moves ahead, no?
Yeah.
He was an operator, sure.
He was an operator.
Jay's partner
double-crossed Jay
killed him,
but what he didn't know
is that Jay
double-crossed him first.
Jay moved the treasure
before he died.
- Seriously?
- Yeah.
And I'm guessing
he moved it here.
I got something.
I found this in the trunk
of that Toyota out in the drive.
Oh, yeah? What is it?
Oh.
[chuckles]
'Treasure.'
You found this
here, in the trunk?
- Yep.
- This is amazing.
No. No, it's awful.
Why?
Because the gold's gone,
maybe forever.
I was slightly off.
When Jay double-crossed
his partner
he-he didn't bring
the gold here.
He used this car
to take the gold
somewhere else entirely.
Or maybe the killer did.
- Whose car is this?
- Mine.
Jay had a key too.
He must have borrowed it.
Or maybe you
moved the gold
after you killed Jay.
- You, screw you, Tark!
- 'No, chill!'
Chill, chill! This isn't
helping. So what now?
Well, now we go home, watch TV.
Rent "Treasure Island"
if it's not too depressing.
Alright, what's
really going on?
Cho and Van Pelt checked
that trunk. There was no coin.
I've baited a trap, Lisbon.
The killer will be compelled
to check on the treasure.
"Bait." The coin. It was
Mr. Shea's, wasn't it?
Well, he's not gonna mind.
It makes for a good story.
His coin will catch a killer.
[car doors close]
Jay never moved
the gold, did he?
Nope, it's still exactly
where he and the killer hid it.
Only now the killer
is gonna feel compelled
to check and see if
it really has moved.
[engine starts]
- So..
- Ahem.
Why didn't you let me in
on your brilliant plan?
Oh, you were very
busy with Greg.
I'm never too busy
to solve a murder.
Well, you seemed to be
very busywith Greg.
Oh, hush.
Alright, I'm hushing.
[Jane]
'Look.'
[intense music]
[Jane]
Ahoy there!
[Lisbon]
Put your hands in the air!
[Jane]
'Ah.'
Gladstone.
And what do we have here?
[latches click]
Aye. That be the treasure.
It was you that
discovered the location
of the Fremont, right?
Yeah.
[Gladstone]
We had a big storm
a month back.
Shifted everything around.
I could see the wreck
on sonar clear as clear.
[Van Pelt]
But you have asthma.
You couldn't dive
for it yourself.
Jay knew salvage...and I
knew he needed the bread bad
so...we partnered up.
And the morning he died?
[Gladstone]
I saw Jay out on the beach.
Thought I'd talk
to him, that's all.
You know,
one partner to another.
I had the hammer
on my belt, you know?
[thud]
I'm a peaceful man.
I can't explain it.
[Van Pelt]
You didn't wanna
share your treasure.
He wanted half,
half of what I found.
'I mean, is that right?'
I don't know
what came over me.
It's called greed.
[birds squawking]
[footsteps approaching]
[Lisbon]
Hey.
Oh, hey.
I cleared it with Chief Anson.
Nobody's gonna prosecute you
for breaking into Jay's boat.
Well, thank you.
You were there to wipe your
wife's prints, weren't you?
Yeah, they met there
a couple of times, her and Jay.
And I knew if you found
out about the affair
you'd get the wrong idea.
So you incriminated yourself.
Hey, she's my wife.
I love her.
I mean, it's gonna take a lot
of work, but I won't give up.
You never did
give up on people.
You're a good man.
She's lucky to have you.
You're strong now,
you know that?
You didn't used
to be so strong.
I bet you're really
good at your job.
Yeah. Yeah,
I'm okay, I think.
You seem happy.
I am.
Yeah. I am.
I'm glad we met again.
You and me, you know?
I'm sorry for running
off the way I did.
Hey, it's no biggie.
Forget it.
[instrumental music]
Take care of yourself.
[music continues]
Was Arkin mad
about the coin?
No, like I said, it's another
story for him to tell.
Always good to
have another story.
Don't be wistful, Lisbon.
Greg was never
the right man for you.
I'm not wistful,
and, no, he wasn't.
Far too intense and particular
for a man like that.
Excuse me?
"Intense and particular?"
- What is that supposed to mean?
- Well, they're good things.
In what ways am I
"intense and particular?"
- Oh, please.
- Tell me.
Well, what ever happened
to that guy from narcotics?
- Jeff?
- Jeff.
Oh, he bit his nails.
See, that's particular.
That is not being particular.
It's a disgusting habit.
[Jane]
'There's intense.'
Is your sister gonna
meet you at the station?
Oh, yeah. She can't wait
to get me in her clutches again.
- Okay, good.
- Yeah.
Got, uh, spaghetti
and meatballs
with the nephews,
and, um
Seattle Community College,
here I come.
Whoo-hoo.
[instrumental music]
This is the right thing.
But I don't
wanna say goodbye.
Maybe you could, uh,
come visit me sometime.
Yeah. Maybe.
[man on PA]
'Last call for
the Coast Moonlight'
'train number 7-14
to Seattle, track 2.'
'Once again, last call
for the Coast Moonlight'
'train number 7-14
to Seattle, track 2.'
"Coast Moonlight."
That sounds romantic.
You better go.
[instrumental music]
Goodbye, Kimball.
[music continues]
Bye.
[theme music]